Finding aid for the Getty Education Institute for the Arts, Grant Files, 1984-2001 IA10021
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Education Institute grant files
1984-2001
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Education Institute for the Arts
Getty Center for Education in the Arts
IA10021
100.5 Linear Feet (101 boxes)
The records, created and/or maintained by Program Officer Vicki Rosenberg, concern the grantmaking activities of the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI) from the mid-1980s until 2001. Rosenberg's files thoroughly cover the full range of GEI grant making activites, including detailed files on District, Regional Institute, and Special Initiative grants. Other GEI initiatives are briefly touched upon in her general adminstrative records. Records are comprised of correspondence, grant proposals, review material, reports, and evaluation materials.
Acquisition Information
Accession 2007.IA.16 was taked as a part of the Legacy Records Appraisal Project during the review of most J. Paul Getty Records entered into storage through 1997.
Accession 2009.IA.38 was taken as part of the Legacy Records Appraisal Project, boxes were discovered in Legacy records appraisal of Communications boxes.
Accession 2010.IA.21 was taken as part of the Legacy Records Appraisal Project, the boxes were found in Foundation records.
Scope and Contents note
The records primarily consist of correspondence, memoranda, grant proposals, review material, reports, statistics, evaluation materials, and printed materials regarding the grant-making and related administrative activities of the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI) from the mid-1980s until 2001. The majority of the records concern the three major prongs of the GEI's grant-making initiatives, District grants, Regional Institute grants, and Special Initiative grants, all of which are thoroughly documented, including the assessment and evaluation aspects of the various projects. A separate set of files include documentation of general administration and chronological correspondence regarding both the GEI's grant initiatives and other GEI initiatives and programs. These materials include records on advisory committee meetings, budget files, conference planning, and Michigan office administration.
The records were created and maintained by Vicki Rosenberg, staff member of the Getty Education Institute, who managed GEI grant funding activities, largely out of an office in Michigan, and reported to GEI Program Director Lani Duke. Upon the dissolution of the GEI, Rosenberg stayed with the grant projects under the loose and general oversight of the Getty Grant Program until the grants expired. Please note that Rosenberg was also heavily involved in the GEI's Children's Television Programing initiative; see the section below on related materials for access to these records.
Access Restrictions
The records in accession 2007.IA.16, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The records in accession 2009.IA.38, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The records in accession 2010.IA.21, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The administrative records described in series 4 are closed to the public for 35 years and are subject to review upon opening.
The following records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Historical Note
In May of 1981, with the anticipated settlement of J. Paul Getty's estate and the disbursement of funds, the J. Paul Getty Trust began intensive exploration to determine how the resources might be best used by the organization in support of the arts world. A year later, the trustees approved a number of recommendations, among which was the creation of a center for developing programs directed at improving the quality and status of arts education. Formally founded in 1982, this center became known as the Getty's Center for Education in the Arts, later known as the Getty Education Institute (GEI) [the abbreviation GEI will be used througout, regardless of the name of the program at the time]. Choosing to focus on the visual arts, the GEI centered it's work around a "discipline-based" approach to art education (DBAE), which had been advocated for by a few art educators for a number of years.
The goal of DBAE was to develop students' abilities to understand and appreciate art. This involved a knowledge of the theories and contexts of art and abilities to respond to as well as to create art. Art was to be taught as an essential component of general education and as a foundation for specialized art study. Content for instruction was derived primarily from the disciplines of aesthetics, art criticism, art history, and art production, disciplines dealing with: (1) conceptions of the nature of art, (2) bases for valuing and judging art, (3) contexts in which art has been created, and (4) processes and techniques for creating art. Content for study was derived from a broad range of the visual arts, including folk, applied, and fine arts from Western and non-Western cultures and from ancient to contemporary times.
Three strategies intended to guide the GEI's programming decisions and assessments. Specifically, the three were: 1) leadership, the GEI needed to create and maintain acceptance of its convictions that arts education was necessary and should be taught in a substantial manner, behaving entrepeneurially when possible and needed; 2) collaboration, the GEI was a new player in arts education and it needed to work with many existing arts stakeholders, some of whom could carry the message with more credibility and to greater number of policy makers; and 3) leveraging, the GEI did not have the resources to effect this change alone, therefore other organizations had to be encouraged to invest their own financial and staff resources.
These emphases resulted in the GEI's decision to focus its efforts into five main program areas: advocacy of the value of arts education, professional development for school and university personnel, theory development to encourage evolution of DBAE, curriculum development to create model instructional materials, and special initiatives to encourage others to adopt DBAE. The program areas then developed a number of specific projects and services, for example the establishment of the Getty Institute for Educators on the Visual Arts (with in-service and district-wide implementation components), DBAE concept development, a pre-service education assessment, a curriculum assessment project, a children's television project, and museum education projects. As these projects were evolving, the GEI also took on responsibility for administering arts education grants from the Getty Grant Program in 1986, with the goal of supporting the development of DBAE programs across the country.
The grant funding activities for school districts, regional consortia, and special initiatives became a substantive part of the GEI's programming from 1986 until 1998. Keeping its three strategies at the core of its grant program, the GEI used the initatives to sponsor actual DBAE curriculum implementation in schools, to support staff development, and to improve the quality and status of arts education.
The grants operated under the oversight of the GEI until 1998, when the Getty Trust made the decision to dissolve the GEI. Since a number of the grants had terms that ran until the end of fiscal year 2001, the final years of some grants were seen to completion under the general oversight of the Getty Grant Program.
Related Materials
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the agencies and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Institutional Archives
Children's Televison Records, 1984-1992, Getty Education Institute for the Arts. Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA10023.
Director Lani Duke's Records, 1986-1998, Getty Education Institute. Institutional Archives, Getty Research Institute, Finding aid no. IA10015.
Organization
Records are organized into four series:
I. District grants, 1984-1992
II. Regional Institute grants, 1996-2001
III. Special Initiative grants, 1986-1998
IV. Vicki Rosenberg's administative records, 1984-2001 (closed to the public for 35 years)
Proposals; Reports; Correspondence; Minutes; Art in education -- United States -- 20th century; Administrative records; Art -- Study and teaching; Arts -- Education, Elementary; Arts -- Study and teaching -- United States; Getty Education Institute for the Arts
- District grants, 1984-1992; I.; 10.75 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
  Records cover the planning, implementation, evaluation and general administration of the District Grant program managed by the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI) from 1986 to 1992. Each of the recipient school districts and their work concerning arts education in their districts are represented in the grant files, as is the GEI's selection, review, and evaluation process. Vicki Rosenberg is the Getty staff member who figures most prominently in the files, though memos and correspondence from Program Director Lani Duke and Trust President Harold Williams are also present. Types of documents found in the records include correspondence, memoranda, notes, proposals, reviews and evaluations, reports, contracts, minutes, and agenda that range in date from 1984 to 1992.
  Arrangement
  The records have been divided into two sections, one for district grant recipients and one for district grants administration. The recipients are in alphabetical order and each has subsections for the planning and, where applicable, implementation phases of their grants. The Administration section is more loosely organized, but it has rough sections concerning general administration, meetings, and evaluations.
  Historical Note
  The GEI took responsibility for administering arts education grants from the Getty Grant Program in 1986, with the goal of supporting the development of DBAE programs across the country. Funds were available to support school district planning and implementation of DBAE programs [hereafter referred to as District Grants], to develop or revise printed DBAE curriculum, and for special initiatives. Shortly thereafter the funding category for developing and revising DBAE curricula was dropped. The Getty first made grants to individual school districts to support DBAE education in 1985. Nine districts were awarded one-year planning grants: two in Maryland, two in Minnesota, one in Nebraska, two in Oregon, one in Arizona, and one in Utah. Four of the districts were then provided two-year implementation grants of up to $100,000: Robbinsdale, Minnesota (1986-1988); Eugene, Oregon (1987-1989); Portland, Oregon (1987-1989); and Provo, Utah (1985-1987). In 1988, the GEI asked Dr.s' Elliot Eisner, Decker Walker, and later Dr.s Al Hurwitz and Gilbert Clark, to conduct a multi-year study for the four implementation sites to determine the extent to which implementation had been accomplished, the quality of those programs, and the likelihood of the programs becoming a permanent part of the districts' instruction. The District Grant program was completed in 1992.
  - District Grant Recipients
    - Arizona Institute for Elementary Art Education:
      - Center for Excellence in Education, First Annual Report, December 31, 1984 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - General Information, 1986 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Interim Report, 1986 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Correspondence and Information, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Interim Report, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - A Statewide Agenda for District Art Programs, January 17, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Assorted Arizona Department of Education Programs (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Internal Memos:
        - 1985-1986 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - January to May 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - June to December 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - January to February 1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - March to June 1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Correspondence:
        - 1985-1986 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - January to March 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - April 1987 (a few from January to March) (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - May to December 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
        - 1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Lists of Individuals Associated with the Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Williams Evaluation, 1986 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Henderson Evaluation, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-9)
      - Thomas Independent Evaluation:
        - Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Contacts (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Report (2 copies) (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
      - Final Report in Six Volumes, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
      - Northern Arizona University: Charles H. Aurand, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
    - Independent School District 281 (Robbinsdale):
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Correspondence 1985-1986 (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
      - Implementation:
        - Year One:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Year One Report (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Site Visit (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Year Two:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Site Visit (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Final Report (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
          - Curriculum Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
      - Independent School District 281: Continuation File, Post Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
      - [Robbinsdale, Minnesota, loose files and reports] (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
      - School District 281, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
    - Indiana University:
      - Planning:
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
      - Implementation:
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-10)
        - Grant Proposal/Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
        - Revised Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-11)
    - Maryland Art Institute:
      - Planning:
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
      - Implementation:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Proposal/Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Revised Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
      - The Maryland Institute, College of Art: F Lazarus, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
    - Omaha Public Schools:
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
      - Implementation:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Proposal/Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
    - Portland Public Schools:
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
      - Implementation:
        - Year One:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Site Visit (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Year One Report (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Year One Report Appendices, 1 (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Year One Report Appendices, 2 (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
        - Year Two:
          - Correspondence, 1989-1981 (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Final Report (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - [Loose report appendices] (Box 2007.IA.16-14)
      - [Loose report appendices and new material] (Box 2007.IA.16-15)
      - Portland Public Schools: Continuation File, Post Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-15)
      - Portland Public Schools, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
    - Provo City Schools:
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
      - Implementation:
        - Year One:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Correspondence 1985-1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Year One Report (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
        - Year Two:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Site Visit (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Final Report (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Final Report Appendix A-D (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-12)
          - Final Report Appendix E-F (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Final Report Appendix G-H (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
          - Final Report Appendix I-J (Box 2007.IA.16-13)
      - Provo City Schools: Vern Brimley, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
    - School District 4J, Eugene, Oregon:
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Review (empty) (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Press (empty) (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
      - Implementation:
        - Year One:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Site Visit (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Final Report, Project Summary/Financial (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Year One Report (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Year Two:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
          - Implementing a Discipline Based Art Curriculum, 2nd Year Report in Eugene, Oregon: (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
          - Project Summary, December 1989 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
          - Documentation of Implementation Activities, December 1989 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
          - Documentation of Assessment and Research Activities, December 1989 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
          - Curricular Materials, December 1989 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
          - Final Report (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - School District 4J (Eugene): Continuation File, Post Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - School District 4J, Eugene, OR, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
    - St. Paul Public Schools:
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Grant Proposal/Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
      - Implementation:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Grant Proposal/Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-16)
      - St Paul Public Schools: David A Bennett, Grant letter (Box 2007.IA.16-80)
  - District Grant Administration
    - Grants Program Administration, 1985-1986:
      - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Reviewers' Guidelines (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Correspondence with Reviewers (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Grant Reviews (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - List of Applicants (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Recommendations to LLD & HW (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Trust Grant Policies (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Grant Proposals for Poster Mailing (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
    - Grants Program Administration, 1987-1988:
      - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Recommendation Memos to LLD & HW (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - National Association of St. Directors of Art Education (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
      - Internal Memos, Continuation, 1989-On (Box 2007.IA.16-70)
    - Administration Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - Grant Guidelines (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - Documentation (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - District Grant Coordination Meetings:
      - January 1987: